Finding aid for Department of Afroamerican and African Studies (University of Michigan) records, 1966-2010 (bulk 1970-1994)
Bentley Historical Library
- VHS Videotapes, 1971-2004
  - 1996-2004
    - "Race Relations in Higher Education", 1997 November 19; [2012140-597]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 2:02:18) (Box 46)
      ("Race Relations in Higher Education: A Prescription for Empowerment and Progress." Presented by Black Issues in Higher Education. Live, interactive satellite videoconference. Moderated by Kojo Nnamdi. Panelists: Christopher Edley, Jr., professor of law at Harvard University and political strategist; Sumi Cho, attorney and instructor at DePaul University; Juan Francisco Lara, access and equity policy specialist and assistant vice chancellor at the University of California, Irvine; Katya Gibel Azoulay, assistant professor of anthropology at Grinnell College,Stanley Fish, professor of English and law at Duke University; and Dr. Raymond A. Winbush, Benjamin Hooks professor of Social justice at Fisk University.)
    - African Student's Association African Nights II, 1998 April 06; [2012140-707]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 2:04:51) (Box 52)
      (Performances by the African Student's Association.)
    - "I'll Make Me a World" (documentary), 1999; [2012140-589]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:55:33) (Box 46)
      ("I'll Make Me a World: A Century of African-American Arts." PBS documentary about African-American art and artists in the 20th century. Directed by Sam Pollard. Narrated by Vanessa Williams.)
    - Jumah Hamilton, director "HIV/AIDS: Pedagogy in Action: 2000"
      - Original, 2000; [2012140-709]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 50:54:00) (Box 52)
        (Director Jumah Hamilton presents "HIV/AIDS: Pedagogy in Action: 2000". This film about the Study Abroad trip to South Africa features footage on location and Interviews with students about the South Africa trip. [708 and 709 are duplicates;709 is original.])
      - Copy, 2000; [2012140-708]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 50:54:00) (Box 52)
    - "Recalling the Future: Art in Contemporary Africa" (documentary), 2000 March; [2012140-598]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 49:51:00) (Box 46)
      ("Recalling the Future: Art in Contemporary Africa." Produced and directed by Claudine Pommier. Executive Director: Cheikh Tidiane N'diaye. Video documentary that poses the questions: What constitutes African art? With which issues do selected artists in Africa locate their practices? How do art-world information brokers construct artists as subjects?")
    - The University of Michigan Sixth Annual Black Celebratory Graduation Program Hill Auditorium (2 hrs.), 2000 April 29; [2012140-710]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:49:33) (Box 52)
      (The Sixth annual University of Michigan Black Celebratory Graduation Program.)
    - Anointed Men of God Mentor Program Trip to U of M on MLK Day, GCBC/Big Brothers Big Sisters, University of Michigan Trip, 2001 January 15; [2012140-711]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 36:34:00) (Box 52)
      (The Greater Christ Baptist Church Anointed Men of God trip the University of Michigan on Martin Luther King Jr. Day)
    - University of Michigan Black Celebratory "1 hour, 39 min.", 2001 April 28; [2012140-712]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:40:30) (Box 52)
      (A University of Michigan Black Celebratory.)
    - Judith Carney, "Rice.," MLK Day Symposium, 2002 January; [2012140-713]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:10:25) (Box 52)
      (An MLK Day Symposium featuring Judith Carney.)
    - A Symposium for the celebration of the life of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson, 2004 March 12
      - Day 1 Tape 1, March 12, 2004; [2012140-714]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:54:09) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Features various presenters. Day 1; 9:14-11am "Amazing Grace" opening song.)
      - Day 1 Tape 2, March 12, 2004; [2012140-715]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:23:39) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Features various presenters. Day 1; 11am-12:30pm.)
      - Day 1 Tape 3, March 12, 2004; [2012140-716]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:08:08) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Features various presenters. Day1; 1:30pm-2:45pm.)
    - A Symposium for the celebration of the life of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson, 2004 March 13
      - Day 2 Tape 1, March 13, 2004; [2012140-717]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:09:45) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Features various presenters. Day 2; 3-4pm.)
      - Day 2 Tape 2, March 13, 2004; [2012140-718]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:55:48) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Features various presenters. Day 2; 9:15-11:30am.)
      - Day 2 Tape 3, March 13, 2004; [2012140-719]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 40:25:00) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Features various presenters. Day 2; 11:30am-12:15pm.)
      - Day 2 Tape 4, March 13, 2004; [2012140-720]; 1 videotape (VHS Videotape; color; sound; 1:37:57) (Box 52)
        (A symposium discussing the life and works of Professor Lemuel A. Johnson. Introduction by Abiola Irele. Features various presenters and poetry readings. Day 2; 3-4pm.)
- Open Reel Video, 1971-1980
  - Val Gray Ward & Co., Part II; Robert Williams, "Community Development, Socialism" and Barbara Ann Teer, "National Black Theatre (Entire Troupe)", 1971 March; [2012140-721]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 41:55:00) (Box 53)
    (Val Gray Ward & Co.,Robert Williams presents "Community Development, Socialism" (part 2) and Barbara Ann Teer and the "National Black Theatre")
  - "Seminar on King Christophe and the Negritude Movement", 1973 April 12; [2012140-722]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:03:26) (Box 53)
    (A "Seminar on King Christophe and the Negritude Movement" is presented.)
  - NCA, Elma Lewis, "Preserving Our Culture", 1973 April 19; [2012140-723]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 59:34:00) (Box 53)
    (NCA, Elma Lewis, and "Preserving Our Culture".)
  - Robert Williams, "Black Activism and Black Politics"
    - Part I, 1979 March 01; [2012140-724]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:08) (Box 53)
      (Robert Williams presents "Black Activism and Black Politics" (part 1).)
    - Part II, 1979 March 01; [2012140-725]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:25) (Box 53)
      (Robert Williams presents "Black Activism and Black Politics" (part 2). James Turner leads a discussion.)
  - James Turner, "Black Studies: Retrospect and Prospect" (complete tape), 1979 March 01; [2012140-726]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:28) (Box 53)
    (James Turner presents "Black Studies: Retrospect and Prospect".)
  - James Turner, "Black Studies: Retrospect and Prospect," Part III and M. Ron Karenga, "The Fundamental Crisis in Black Life: Analysis and Alternatives" Part I, 1979 March 01; [2012140-727]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:32) (Box 53)
  - M. Ron Karenga, "The Fundamental Crisis in Black Life: Analysis and Alternatives" Part II, 1979 March 01; [2012140-728]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:17) (Box 53)
    (M. Ron Karenga presents "The Fundamental Crisis in Black Life: Analysis and Alternatives" (Part II).)
  - Panel, "The Organizations and Significance of BAM," Part I of 3, "Attn Cynthia Stevens, Attn Ron Harris, Attn David Lewis, Prof. Niara Sudarkasa" 1:30-3:30, 1980 March 20; [2012140-729]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:49) (Box 53)
    (Discussion with: Attorney Cynthia Stevens, Attorney Ron Harris, Attorney David Lewis, Professor Niara Sudarkasa. There is one panel: "The Organizations and Significance of BAM" (part 1).)
  - Smith, Varner, Hefner, Mann, Yates, Panel, "Perspectives on BAM from the University Community," 4:00pm (Part I), 1980 March 20; [2012140-730]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:04:52) (Box 53)
    (Discussion with: Smith, Varner, Hefner, Mann, Yates. Two panel discussions: "Perspectives on BAM from the University Community" (part 1).)
  - Smith, Varner, Hefner, Mann, Yates, Panel, "Perspectives on BAM from the University Community," 4:00pm (Part II) and Panel: "The Challenge of BAM for the 1980s" 5:30pm (Part I), 1980 March 20; [2012140-731]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:05:10) (Box 53)
    (Discussion with: Smith, Varner, Hefner, Mann, Yates. Two panel discussions: "Perspectives on BAM from the University Community" (part 2) and "The Challenge of BAM for the 1980s" (part 1).)
  - Jemadari Kamara, Ben Newhouse, Vicky Rowels, Virna Hobbs, Janice O'Neal, Obika Gray, Panel, "The Challenge of BAM for the 1980s, 1980 March 20; [2012140-732]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:05:05) (Box 53)
    (Jemadari Kamara, Ben Newhouse, Vicky Rowels, Virna Hobbs, Janice O'Neal, Obika Gray, Panel, "The Challenge of BAM for the 1980s" (part 2).)
  - Howard Shapiro, "UM: A Decade After BAM" and Panel: "The Organization and Significance of BAM", 1980 March 21
    - Tape 1, 1980 March 21; [2012140-733]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 1:05:00) (Box 53)
      (Howard Shapiro, "UM: A Decade After BAM" and Panel: "The Organization and Significance of BAM". Also a discussion with question/answers.)
    - Tape 2, 1980 March 21; [2012140-734]; 1 videotape (Open Reel Videotape; b/w; sound; 34:26:00) (Box 53)
- Reel-to-reel audiotape, 1971; 1980
  - Harold Cruse, Leroi Jones, Jimmy Garrett (Interviews), undated (Box 54)
    - Part 1
      - Segment 1, [2012140-SR-735-1-1]; (Interview with Harold Cruse discussing: Cruse's book, Cruse's views on black intellectualism, the black experience in America.)
      - Segment 2, [2012140-SR-735-1-2]; (Unidentified speaker discusses: oppression, integration, opium. Possibly Robert Williams (by content) but not verified.)
    - Part 2, [2012140-SR-735-2]; (Imamu Baraka (Leroi Jones) interview discussing: schools, curriculums, politics, black communities.)
  - Harold Cruse; "On the Significance of Black Culture," Black Liberation Week, 1969 March; (Lecture/Discussion by Harold Cruse titles "On the Significance of Black Culture". Held during one of the first Black Liberation Week gatherings. Art and film.) (Box 54)
    - Part 1, [2012140-SR-736-1]
    - Part 2, [2012140-SR-736-2]
  - Side I: Robert Williams and James V. Turner Side II: Jimmy Garrett and Phil Lee, Community Center Side, 1971 March 17 - 1971 March 19 (Box 54)
    (Side 1 event May also be documented on a U-Matic Video, and on open reel video;)
    - Part 1, 1971 March 19; [2012140-SR-737-1]; (Black Liberation Week at the University of Michigan. A symposium/workshop titled: "The Black Movement: Ideologies and Issues". Presented by Robert WIlliams. Subjects: self-determination, China, slavery, oppression, welfare. James V. Turner on land, economic development, change in black communities.)
    - Part 2, 1971 March 17; [2012140-SR-737-2]; (Black Liberation Week. Phil Lee on Malcolm X Liberation University (ideology). Jimmy Garrett on Center for Black Education.)
  - "Tribute to Robert Hayden," Parts I, II and III, Stearns Building, University of Michigan, WUOM, 1980 February 24 (Box 54)
    (3 reels)
    (These available on cassettes)
    - Part I, [2012140-SR-738-1]; (Ali Mazrui introduces a talk on "The Poetics of Robert Hayden". Musical performance by Orl Moses. Reading by Randall.)
    - Part II, [2012140-SR-139-1]; (Poetry reading, musical performances, discussion, dramatic reading, reading of plaque Onye Lockhard(?).)
    - Part III, [2012140-SR-740-1]; (Poetry reading, discussion, musical performance, closing.)
- DV Cam tapes, 1998-2000
  - South Africa Study Abroad Program, 1998-2000
    - SAIO (South African Initiative Office) Awards ceremony, Undated; [2012140-741]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 1:02:24) (Box 54)
      (SAIO Awards ceremony led by Oscar Barber(?) Executive Director of the South African Initiative Office. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Interview with Nozizwe M. Routledge, [circa 1998 or 1999]; [2012140-742]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 51:49:00) (Box 54)
      (An Interview with Nozizwe M. Routledge in the second half of 1998 or the first half of 1999. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Moody Training Program Lecture 3., 1999 February 17; [2012140-743]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 37:13:00) (Box 54)
      (Students discuss issues related to race and their experiences through ice breaker activities including bingo in preparation for the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Teshome Wagaw, Lecture 4, tape 1. Students discuss issues related to South Africa., 1999; [2012140-744]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 1:02:26) (Box 54)
      (Students receive information and answer questions about South Africa. Thoughts about safety, violence, and crime in South Africa. Students learn about issues of poverty, violence, crime, and education in South Africa. Lecture by Teshome Wagaw. Part of the preparation for the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Lecture 6, 1999 March 17; [2012140-745]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 44:33:00) (Box 54)
      (A lecture covering various topics about South Africa. In preparation for the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Bernadette and friend guest lecture in Johannesburg., 2000 July 04; [2012140-746]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 59:49:00) (Box 54)
      (Bernadette and a friend give a lecture about AIDS in Africa. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Safari trip, God's Window, and pot holes., 2000 June 30; [2012140-747]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 1:01:25) (Box 54)
      (Students go on a guided safari and listen to a lecture. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Jumah and Sam give presentations to soccer team., 2000 July 04; [2012140-748]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 33:44:00) (Box 54)
      (Jumah and Sam teach about biology and HIV to the soccer team. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - South Africa Study Abroad trip. Interviews with group about first 3 weeks were in S. Africa., 2000 June 09; [2012140-749]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 28:19:00) (Box 54)
      (Students are interviewed about their experiences on the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Interview - Mr(s?) Moffat, 2000 July 05; [2012140-750]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 29:15:00) (Box 54)
      (Interview with Mr(s?) Moffat. Talks about Nelson Mandela. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - First interviews about South Africa Study Abroad trip with students and faculty., [2000]; [2012140-751]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 58:34:00) (Box 54)
      (These are the first interviews about the South Africa Study Abroad program before the trip. Interview with: Dr. Moody, Prof. Haniff, Phyllis Gayden, Rashad Nelms, Alexis Oliver, Kylie Anchura(?), Betsy Havens, Hilary Patrick, Sabrina Ollie, Diana Dalehay(?), Lesley Welch, Elizabeth Arkonloyay(?), Jumah Hamilton. Latonia, Julie Frye(?).)
    - Interviews about the trip to South Africa: Jumah Hamilton, Lesley., [2000]; [2012140-752]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 20:30) (Box 54)
      (Interview with Jumah Hamilton and Lesly Welch about the South Africa Study Abroad program..)
    - Interviews about the Study Abroad to South Africa with: Alexis, Kylie, Elizabeth, Jumah (1/2), [2000]; [2012140-753]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 1:00:00) (Box 54)
      (Student interviews about the South Africa Study Abroad program with: Alexis Oliver, Kylie Anchura, Elizabeth Arkonloyay(?), Jumah Hamilton.)
    - Second interviews a week before the S. Africa trip: Rashad, Hilary, Phyllis, Sabrina, Diana, 2000 May 24; [2012140-754]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 54:42:00) (Box 54)
      (Interviews one week before South Africa Study Abroad program. Students interviews: Rashad Nelms, Hilary Patrick, Phyllis Gayden, Sabrina Ollie, and Diana Dalehay(?).)
    - South Africa meeting no. 3, 2000 March 10; [2012140-755]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 52:54:00) (Box 54)
      (Various topics are discussed about the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Chris Hani (Hari?) teaches back; presentation of certificates; listing to President, Mbeki's speech on TV., [2000]; [2012140-756]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 31:45:00) (Box 54)
      (HIV. Chris Hani (Hari?), presentation of certificates, listing to president, Mbeki's speech on TV. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Mbeki's speech on TV. (Box 54)
    - Les and Sabrina, Maguboni(?) and Daisy (2 of 2), [2000]; [2012140-757]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 16:46) (Box 54)
      (HIV and STDs. Interviews with: Les,Sabrina, Maguboni(?), and Daisy. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Jumah and Kyle cptn; Lesley and Sabrina; traditional healers (1 of 2), [2000]; [2012140-758]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 1:02:44) (Box 54)
      (HIV. Talks by Jumah, Kyle, Lesley, Sabrina and traditional healers. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Traditional healers presentation; Leslie and Sabrina, [2000]; [2012140-759]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 47:38:00) (Box 54)
      (HIV. Traditional healers presentation: Leslie and Sabrina. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Langa Certificate presentations, [2000]; [2012140-760]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 18:44) (Box 54)
      (Certificate presentations. Presentations about HIV. Langa township, Cape Town. South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Student interviews: Pedagogy of Action Study Abroad to South Africa, [2000]; [2012140-761]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 49:17:00) (Box 54)
      (Pedagogy of Action Study Abroad in South Africa. Interviews with students: Betsy Havens, Samantha Brown, Rashad Nelms(?), Phyllis Gayden(?). South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Documenting travel to South Africa, [2000]; [2012140-762]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 21:26) (Box 54)
      (Contains footage of students traveling to South Africa. Students are interviewed at the airport. There is some footage of South Africa. Part of the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - Student interviews: Pedagogy of Action Study Abroad to South Africa, [2000]; [2012140-763]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 55:58:00) (Box 54)
      (Pedagogy of Action Study Abroad in South Africa. Interviews with students: Tonya Payne(?), Hilary Patrick, Kylie Anchura(?), Julie Frye(?), Sabrina Ollie(?). Part of the South Africa Study Abroad program.)
    - "The Barbecue" (Braai), [2000]; [2012140-764]; 1 videotape (DVCam; color; sound; 12:43) (Box 54)
      (Students and teachers are interviewed at a South African barbecue (Xhosa). Part of the South Africa Study Abroad program. Recording is very dark during the first 2 minutes.)
Related Material
Related collections at the Bentley Library include the papers of CAAS faculty members Lemuel A. Johnson, Ali A. Mazrui and Willis C. Patterson. The collections of choral director Eva Jessye, bandleader Andy Kirk, and of baritone Todd Duncan were transferred from the CAAS library to the Bentley in 2008.
In 2014 Bentley Historical Library digitized select documents relating to the Black Action Movement I, II and III.